"How to Boost Fat Burning by 25%"
We now know why fiber-rich foods
can have such a powerful effect
on our weight.
The evidence for the role
of fiber in weight control
started with so-called
ecological studies.
These involve comparing
population averages,
and researchers noted
that populations
with extraordinary fiber intakes
tend to have
negligible obesity rates.
For example, the average
Pima Indian in Mexico
eating their traditional
high-fiber diet
centered around
the "three sisters"
(corn, beans, and squash)
is normal weight,
but the average Pima on U.S.
reservations has obesity.
The problem with dealing
with population averages
is that we don’t know
if the individuals eating
the higher-fiber diets
are themselves necessarily
the ones protected from obesity.
What do we see
in cohort studies,
where individuals and their
diets are followed over time?
A cohort study
of overweight youth found
that the amount of fiber found
in a single half cup
daily serving of beans,
about 6 grams,
over about a two-year period,
was associated
with a profound 25% difference
in abdominal obesity.
In about the same timeframe,
in middle-aged women,
each 2-gram increase
in daily fiber
was associated
with a weight decrease
of about a pound (0.45 kg).
The postpartum period
seems to be a critical time
for women to be
at risk of retaining
the weight put on
during pregnancy.
A study of hundreds of new moms
followed for the first
five months
found that inadequate
fiber intake
appeared to increase
obesity risk by 24%.
And it’s not just women.
A cohort that included
tens of thousands of men
followed for years
concluded that an increase
in fiber consumption
of just 10 grams a day
may prevent about 10% of weight
gain within the population.
Overall, the evidence from these
kinds of observational studies
is strong that
"Increasing consumption
of dietary fiber
with fruits, vegetables,
whole grains, and legumes
across the life cycle
is a critical step in stemming
the epidemic of obesity."
These studies can control
for nondietary influences
such as physical activity
by equipping people with gadgets
to measure their movement,
but there may be uncontrolled
confounding dietary factors.
Think about the list
of high-fiber foods--
fruits, vegetables,
whole grains, and beans.
Maybe fiber intake is just
a marker for the intake
of healthy foods,
and there are dozens of reasons
why eating whole plant foods
could lead to weight loss that
have nothing to do with fiber.
To know if there’s
a cause-and-effect relationship
between fiber and weight loss,
you need to put it to the test
in interventional trials.
That’s where colonic infusions
can come in handy.
In a randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled
crossover study,
researchers showed that people’s
metabolism can be boosted
within 30 minutes of
an infusion into their rectums
of short-chain fatty acids,
the molecules our gut bacteria
make when we feed them fiber.
The study used the amounts
we’d expect to create ourselves
just from eating
a high-fiber diet.
Not only did the study
participants get an increase
in their resting metabolic rate
(the amount of calories burned
just by existing),
but specifically, their fat
oxidation shot up as well,
increasing the amount
of fat they were burning
by more than 25%.
This translates to about
an extra third of a pat
of butter’s worth of fat
burned off their body within
two hours of the infusion.
Colonic catheters aside,
we can get short-chain
fatty acids directly
and get the same little bump
in resting metabolic rate
and whole-body fat breakdown
in addition
to a decrease in appetite.
So again, fiber may work
on both sides
of the energy balance equation.
But does that decreased appetite
actually translate
into eating less?
We’ll find out next.